<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "rfc2629.dtd" [
<!ENTITY RFC2119 PUBLIC "" "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2119.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC5305 PUBLIC "" "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.5305.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC7810 PUBLIC "" "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.7810.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC7916 PUBLIC "" "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.7916.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC2205 PUBLIC "" "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2205.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC1195 PUBLIC "" "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.1195.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC7752 PUBLIC "" "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.7752.xml">
]>
<?rfc toc="yes"?>
<?rfc tocompact="yes"?>
<?rfc tocdepth="3"?>
<?rfc tocindent="yes"?>
<?rfc symrefs="yes"?>
<?rfc sortrefs="yes"?>
<?rfc comments="yes"?>
<?rfc inline="yes"?>
<?rfc compact="yes"?>
<?rfc subcompact="no"?>
<rfc category="std" docName="draft-hegde-isis-advertising-te-protocols-03" ipr="trust200902">
<front>
<title> Advertising TE protocols in IS-IS</title>
<author initials="S." surname="Hegde" fullname="Shraddha Hegde">
<organization>Juniper Networks</organization>
<address>
<postal>
<street>Embassy Business Park</street>
<city>Bangalore</city>
<region>KA</region>
<code>560093</code>
<country>India</country>
</postal>
<email>shraddha@juniper.net</email>
</address>
</author>

<author fullname="Chris Bowers" initials="C." surname="Bowers">
<organization>Juniper Networks</organization>
<address>
<postal>
<street>1194 N. Mathilda Ave.</street>
<city>Sunnyvale</city>
<region>CA</region>
<code>94089</code>
<country>US</country>
</postal>
<email>cbowers@juniper.net</email>
</address>
</author>

<author fullname="Paul Mattes" initials="P." surname="Mattes">
<organization>Microsoft</organization>
<address>
<postal>
<street>One Microsoft Way</street>
<city>Redmond</city>
<region>WA</region>
<code>98052</code>
<country>US</country>
</postal>
<email>pamattes@microsoft.com</email>
</address>
</author>

<author fullname="Mohan Nanduri" initials="M." surname="Nanduri">
<organization>Microsoft</organization>
<address>
<postal>
<street>One Microsoft Way</street>
<city>Redmond</city>
<region>WA</region>
<code>98052</code>
<country>US</country>
</postal>
<email>mnanduri@microsoft.com</email>
</address>
</author>

<author fullname="Spencer Giacalone" initials="S." surname="Giacalone">
<organization>Microsoft</organization>
<address>
<postal>
<street>One Microsoft Way</street>
<city>Redmond</city>
<region>WA</region>
<code>98052</code>
<country>US</country>
</postal>
<email>Spencer.Giacalone@microsoft.com</email>
</address>
</author>

<author fullname="Imtiyaz Mohammad" initials="I." surname="Mohammad">
<organization>Arista Networks</organization>
<address>
<postal>
<street>Global Tech Park</street>
<city>Bangalore</city>
<region>KA</region>
<code>560103</code>
<country>India</country>
</postal>
<email>imtiyaz@arista.com</email>
</address>
</author>

<date year="2017"/>
<area>Routing</area>
<workgroup>IS-IS WG</workgroup>
<keyword>MPLS</keyword>
<keyword>IGP</keyword>
<keyword>IS-IS</keyword>
<abstract>

<t>  This document defines a mechanism to indicate which traffic engineering
protocols are enabled on a link in IS-IS.  It does so by introducing a new 
traffic-engineering protocol sub-TLV for TLV-22.
This document also describes mechanisms to address backward 
compatibility issues for implementations that have not yet been upgraded 
to software that understands this new sub-TLV.  
</t> 

</abstract>
<note title="Requirements Language">
<t>The key words "MUST", "MUST NOT", "REQUIRED", "SHALL", "SHALL NOT",
"SHOULD", "SHOULD NOT", "RECOMMENDED", "MAY", and "OPTIONAL" in this
document are to be interpreted as described in <xref target="RFC2119">RFC 2119</xref>.</t>
</note>
</front>
<middle>

<section title="Introduction" anchor='intro'>

<t> IS-IS extensions for traffic engineering are specified in <xref 
target="RFC5305"/>. <xref target="RFC5305"/> defines several link 
attributes such as administrative group, maximum link bandwidth, and 
shared risk link groups (SRLGs) which can be used by traffic engineering 
applications. Additional link attributes for traffic engineering have 
subsequently been defined in other documents as well. Most recently
<xref target="RFC7810"/> defined link attributes for delay, loss, 
and measured bandwidth utilization. </t> 

<t>The primary consumers of these traffic engineering link attributes 
have been RSVP-based applications that use the advertised link 
attributes to compute paths which will subsequently be signalled using 
RSVP-TE. However, these traffic engineering link attributes have also 
been used by other applications, such as IP/LDP fast-reroute using 
loop-free alternates as described in <xref target="RFC7916"/>. In the 
future, it is likely that traffic engineering applications based on 
Segment Routing <xref target="I-D.ietf-spring-segment-routing"/> will 
also use these link attributes. </t> 

<t> Existing IS-IS standards do not provide a mechanism to explicitly 
indicate whether or not RSVP has been enabled on a link. Instead, 
different RSVP-TE implementations have used the presence of certain 
traffic engineering sub-TLVs in IS-IS to infer that RSVP signalling is 
enabled on a given link.  A study was conducted with various vendor 
implementations to determine which traffic engineering sub-TLVs
cause an implementation to infer that RSVP signalling is enabled on a link.
The results are shown in <xref target="fig_study"/>. </t>

<figure anchor="fig_study" title="Traffic engineering Sub-TLVs that cause
implementation X, Y, or Z to infer that RSVP signalling is enabled on a link"
align="center">
<artwork align="center">
+--------+--------------------------------------------+
| TLV/   | Sub-TLV name                |Implementation|
|sub-TLV |                             +--------------+
|        |                             | X  | Y  | Z  |
+--------+--------------------------------------------+
|22      |Extended IS Reachability TLV | N  | N  | N  |
|22/3    |Administrative group (color) | N  | Y  | Y  |
|22/4    |Link Local/Remote ID         | N  | N  | N  |
|22/6    |IPV4 Interface Address       | N  | N  | N  |                      
|22/8    |IPV4 Neighbor Address        | N  | N  | N  |  
|22/9    |Max Link Bandwidth           | N  | Y  | Y  |
|22/10   |Max Reservable Link Bandwidth| N  | Y  | Y  |
|22/11   |Unreserved Bandwidth         | Y  | Y  | Y  | 
|22/14   |Extended Admin Group         | N  | Y  | N  |  
|22/18   |TE Default Metric            | N  | N  | N  |
|22/20   |Link Protection Type         | N  | Y  | Y  |
|22/21   |Interface Switching          | N  | Y  | Y  |
|        | Capability                  |    |    |    |
|22/22   |TE Bandwidth Constraints     | N  | Y  | Y  |  
|22/33-39|TE Metric Extensions(RFC7180)| N  | N  | N  | 
|138     |SRLG TLV                     | N  | Y  | Y  | 
+--------+--------------------------------------------+
</artwork>
</figure>
<t>The study indicates that the different implementations use the 
presence of different sub-TLVs under TLV 22 (or the presence of TLV 138) 
to infer that RSVP signalling is enabled on a link. It is possible that 
other implementations may use other sub-TLVs to infer that RSVP is 
enabled on a link.</t> 

<t> This document defines a standard way to indicate whether or not 
RSVP, segment routing, or another future protocol is enabled on a link. 
In this way, implementations will not have to infer whether or not RSVP 
is enabled based on the presence of different sub-TLVs, but can use the 
explicit indication. When network operators want to use a non-RSVP 
traffic engineering application (such as IP/LDP FRR or segment routing), 
they will be able to advertise traffic engineering sub-TLVs and explicitly 
indicate what traffic engineering protocols are enabled on a link. </t> 

</section>

<section anchor="sec_motivation" title="Goals">

<t>
<list style="numbers">
<t> The solution should allow the TE protocol enabled on a link to be communicated unambiguously. </t>
<t> The solution should decouple the advertisement of which TE protocols are enabled on a link from 
    the advertisement of other TE attributes.</t>
<t> The solution should be backward compatible so that nodes that do 
    not understand the new advertisement do not cause issues for existing RSVP deployments.</t>
<t> The solution should be extensible for new protocols.</t>
<t> The solution should try to limit any increases to the quantity and size of link 
	state advertisements.</t>
</list>
</t>

<section anchor="sec_unambiguous" title="Explicit and unambiguous indication of TE protocol">
<t> Communicating unambiguously which TE protocol is enabled on a link is 
important to be able to share this information with other consumers through 
other protocols, aside from just the IGP.  For example, for a 
network running both RSVP-TE and SR, it will be useful 
to communicate which TE protocols are enabled on which links via 
BGP-LS <xref target="RFC7752"/> to a central controller.  Typically,
BGP-LS relies on the IGP to distribute IGP topology and traffic engineering
information so that only a few BGP-LS sessions with the central controller
are needed.  In order for a router running a BGP-LS session to 
a central controller to correctly communicate what TE 
protocols are enabled on the links in the IGP domain, that information
first needs to be communicated unambiguously within the IGP itself.  As 
 <xref target="fig_study"/> illustrates, that is currently not the case.
</t>
</section>

</section>

<section title='Solution' anchor='sec_solution'>

<section title='Traffic-engineering protocol sub-TLV'>

<t> A new Traffic-engineering protocol sub-TLV is added in the 
TLV 22 <xref target="RFC5305"/> or TLV 222 to indicate the protocols 
enabled on the link.  The sub-TLV has flags in the value field to indicate 
the protocol enabled on the link. The length field is variable to allow 
the flags field to grow for future requirements.</t> 

<figure anchor="Traffic_engineering_protocol_sub_tlv" title="Traffic-Engineering Protocol sub-TLV">
<artwork align="center">

Type  : TBD suggested value 40
Length: Variable
Value :
  0                   1                   2                   3
  0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1
 +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
 |                         Flags                                 |
 +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+

</artwork>
</figure>
<t>
Type : TBA (suggested value 40)
<vspace blankLines="1" />
Length: variable (in bytes)
<vspace blankLines="1" />
Value: The value field consists of bits indicating the protocols enabled on the link.
This document defines the two protocol values below.
</t>
<figure anchor="Protocol_values" title="Flags for the protocols">
<artwork align="center">
+----------+-------------------------------+
| Value    | Protocol Name                 | 
+----------+-------------------------------+   
|0x01      | RSVP                          |   
+----------+-------------------------------+
|0x02      | Segment Routing               |
+----------+-------------------------------+
   
</artwork>
</figure>

<t> The RSVP flag is set to one to indicate that RSVP-TE is enabled on a link. 
The RSVP flag is set to zero to indicate that RSVP-TE is not enabled on a link. </t>

<t> The Segment Routing flag is set to one to indicate that Segment 
Routing is enabled on a link. The Segment Routing flag is set to zero to 
indicate that Segment Routing is not enabled on a link.</t> 

<t> All undefined flags MUST be set to zero on transmit and 
ignored on receipt. </t> 

<t> An implementation that supports the TE protocol sub-TLV and sends TLV 
22 MUST advertise the TE protocol sub-TLV in TLV 22 for that link, even 
when both the RSVP and SR flags are set to zero. In other words, 
whenever the TE protocol sub-TLV is supported, it MUST be sent, even if 
no TE protocols are enabled on the link. This allows a receiving router 
to determine whether or not the sending router is capable of sending the 
TE protocol sub-TLV. </t> 

<t> A router supporting the TE protocol sub-TLV which receives
an advertisement for a link containing TLV 22 with 
the TE protocol sub-TLV present SHOULD respect the values of the 
flags in the TE protocol sub-TLV. The receiving router SHOULD only 
consider links with a given TE protocol enabled for inclusion in 
a path using that TE protocol.  Conversely, links for which 
the TE protocol sub-TLV is present, but for which the TE protocol flag 
is not set to one, SHOULD NOT be included in any TE CSPF 
computations on the receiving router for the protocol in question.</t>

<t> The ability for a receiving router to determine whether or not the 
sending router is capable of sending the TE protocol sub-TLV is also 
used for backward compatibility as described in <xref 
target="sec_back_compat"/>. </t> 

<t> An implementation that supports the TE protocol sub-TLV SHOULD be able to 
advertise TE sub-TLVs without enabling RSVP-TE signalling on
the link. </t>

</section>

<section anchor="sec_sr_flag" title='Segment Routing flag considerations'>
<t>The Segment Routing (SR) architecture assumes that the SR topology is 
congruent with the IGP topology. The path described by a prefix segment 
is computed using the SPF algorithm applied to the IGP topology, which 
is the same as the SR topology.  Therefore, the presence or absence of 
the Segment Routing flag MUST NOT be interpreted as modifying the SR 
topology, which is always congruent with the IGP topology. 
</t> 

<t>It is however useful for a centralized application (or an ingress 
router) to know whether or not it should expect to be able to forward 
traffic over a given link using labels distributed via SR. If a link is 
advertised with the TE protocol sub-TLV and the SR flag set to zero, 
then a centralized application can assume that traffic sent with a 
prefix segment whose path crosses that link is unlikely to be forwarded 
across that link. With this information, a centralized application can 
decide to use a different path for that traffic by using a different 
label stack. 
</t> 

</section>


</section>


<section anchor="sec_back_compat" title='Backward compatibility'>
<t>Routers running older software that do not understand the new 
Traffic-Engineering protocol sub-TLV will continue to interpret the 
presence of some sub-TLVs in TLV 22 or the presence of TLV 138 as 
meaning that RSVP is enabled a link. A network operator may not want to or 
be able to upgrade all routers in the domain at the same time. 
There are two backward compatibility scenarios to consider 
depending on whether the router that doesn't understand the
new TE protocol sub-TLV is an RSVP-TE ingress router or an RSVP-TE transit router.  
</t> 

<section anchor="sec_upgraded_transit" title='Scenario with upgraded RSVP-TE transit 
router but RSVP-TE ingress router not upgraded'>
<t> An upgraded RSVP-TE transit router is able to explicitly indicate
that RSVP is not enabled on a link by advertising the TE protocol 
sub-TLV with the RSVP flag set to zero. However, an RSVP-TE ingress router that 
has not been upgraded to understand the new TE protocol sub-TLV will not 
understand that RSVP-TE is not enabled on the link, and may include the 
link on a path computed for RSVP-TE. When the network tries to signal 
an explicit path LSP using RSVP-TE through that link, it will fail. In 
order to avoid this scenario, an operator can use the mechanism 
described below. </t> 

<t> For this scenario, the basic idea is to use the existing 
administrative group link attribute as a means of preventing existing 
RSVP implementations from using a link. The network operator defines an
administrative group to mean that RSVP is not enabled on a 
link. We call this admin group the RSVP-not-enabled admin group. If the 
operator needs to advertise a TE sub-TLV (maximum link bandwidth, for 
example) on a link, but doesn't want to enable RSVP on that link, then 
the operator also advertises the RSVP-not-enabled admin group on that 
link. The operator can then use existing mechanisms to exclude links 
advertising the RSVP-not-enabled admin group from the constrained 
shortest path first (CSPF) computation used by RSVP. This will prevent 
RSVP implementations from attempting to signal RSVP-TE LSPs across links 
that do not have RSVP enabled. Once the entire network domain is 
upgraded to understand the TE protocol sub-TLV in this draft, the 
configuration involving the RSVP-not-enabled admin group is no longer 
needed for this network.</t> 
</section>

<section anchor="sec_upgraded_ingress" title='Scenario with upgraded RSVP-TE ingress 
router but RSVP-TE transit router not upgraded'>
 <t> The other scenario to consider is when the RSVP-TE ingress router 
has been upgraded to understand the TE protocol sub-TLV, but the RSVP-TE 
transit router has not. In this case, the transit router has not been 
upgraded, so it is not yet capable of sending the TE protocol sub-TLV.  If
the transit router has RSVP-TE enabled on a link, we would like for the RSVP-TE
ingress router to still be able to use the link for RSVP-TE paths.
While it is possible to describe a solution for this scenario that 
makes use of administrative groups, we describe a simpler solution below.</t>

<t> The solution for this scenario relies on the following observation. 
If the RSVP-TE ingress router can understand that the transit router is 
not capable of sending the TE protocol sub-TLV, then it can continue 
inferring whether or not RSVP-TE is enabled on the transit router links 
based on the presence of TE sub-TLVs, just as it does today.</t> 

<t> To accomplish this, we require an upgraded router to send the TE 
protocol sub-TLV if it sends TLV 22, even when both the RSVP and SR 
flags are set to zero.  In other words, whenever the TE protocol sub-TLV 
is supported, it MUST be sent, even if no TE protocols are enabled on the link.
  see <xref target="sec_solution"/>. This allows 
the receiving router to interpret the absence of the TE-protocol sub-TLV 
together with presence of TLV 22 to mean that the sending router has not 
been upgraded. This allows the upgraded RSVP-TE ingress router to 
distinguish between transit routers that have been upgraded and those 
that haven't. When the transit router has been upgraded, then the 
RSVP-TE ingress router uses the information in the TE protocol sub-TLV. 
When the transit router has not been upgraded, then RSVP-TE ingress 
router contines to infer whether or not RSVP-TE is enabled on the 
transit router links based on the presence of TE sub-TLVs, just as it 
does today. The solution for this scenario requires no configuration on 
the part of network operators.</t> 

</section>

<section anchor="sec_need_for_long_term" title='Need for a long term solution'>
<t> The use of the adminstrative group link attribute to prevent an 
RSVP-TE ingress router from computing a path using a given link is
an effective short term workaround to allow networks to incrementally upgrade 
the routers to software that understands the new TE-protocol sub-TLV.
One might also consider a long term solution based solely on the use 
of operator-defined adminstrative groups to communicate the TE protocol enabled
on a link.  However, we do not consider this workaround to be an effective long term solution
because it relies on operator configuration that would have to be maintained
in the long term.  As discussed in <xref target="sec_motivation"/>, continuing to
have to infer which TE protocol is enabled on a link also limits our ability 
to communicate this information unambiguously in an interoperable manner for use
by other applications such as central controllers.
</t>
</section>

</section>

<section title='Security Considerations' anchor='sec-con'>
<t>
This document does not introduce any further security issues other
than those discussed in <xref target="RFC1195"/> and <xref target="RFC5305"/>.
</t>
</section>
<section anchor="IANA" title="IANA Considerations">

<t>This specification updates one IS-IS registry:</t>
<t><vspace blankLines="1"/></t>

<t> The extended IS reachability TLV Registry</t>
 <t> i) Traffic-engineering Protocol sub-tlv = Suggested value 40</t>
</section>
<section title='Acknowledgements'>
<t>The authors thank Alia Atlas, Les Ginsberg, and Peter Psenak for  
helpful discussions on the topic of this draft.</t> 

</section>


</middle>
<back>

<references title='Normative References'>
&RFC2119;
&RFC5305;
&RFC7810;
<?rfc include="http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml3/reference.I-D.draft-ietf-spring-segment-routing-09.xml"?>
</references>
<references title='Informative References'>
&RFC7916;
&RFC1195;
&RFC7752;
</references>

</back>
</rfc>